Guide to the Helen M. Stummer Photographs and Papers 1976-2001 PR 235
New-York Historical Society
Helen M. Stummer photographs and papers
1976-2001
New-York Historical Society
Stummer, Helen M., 1936-
PR 235
2.5 Linear feet in 3 boxes
Photographs of residents of East 6th Street in Manhattan, New York City, and related material from the photographer.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 2003 a total of 22 photographs were acquired from the photographer in a combined purchase/donation transaction. Additional images and other documentary material were donated by the photographer in August 2008. A memoir was added in March 2013.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Helen M. Stummer was born in 1936. She holds a bachelor's degree in fine arts from Kean College, and a masters degree in Visual Sociology from Vermont College. Before becoming a photographer, Stummer was a painter. She began taking photographs in 1975, enrolling in classes at the International Center for Photography in New York City, in order to better document subjects for her paintings.
Stummer considers herself a Visual Sociologist. She has focused her camera on photographing economically disadvantaged communities, both in urban and rural settings. In addition to the photographs taken on East 6th Street found in this collection, she has documented inhabitants of the city of Newark, New Jersey, as well as communities in rural Maine and in Guatemala.
Stummer's photographs have been widely published and exhibited. More information on Stummer can be found on her website, www.hmstummer.com.
Scope and Content Note
The Helen M. Stummer Photographs and Papers span the period from 1976 to 2001 and primarily contains photographs taken on East 6th Street in New York City. The collection also holds some of the photographer's archive relating to these photographs, including audiocassettes, a videocassette, an artist's book and a memoir.
While Stummer was enrolled in photography classes at the International Center for Photography, she was encouraged to continue an earlier interest in photographing children. She arranged to go to the Children's Aid Society's Sloane Center on East 6th Street between Avenues B and C. At that time the street was considered part of the Lower East Side neighborhood, and was inhabited mainly by poor Puerto Rican and African American families. Stummer photographed children both inside the Center and outside on the streets. Over the course of several years, she befriended many East 6th Street residents, and photographed important events in their lives. She also conducted oral interviews with some of the people she met and photographed.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in two series.
Missing Title
Series I: Photographs
Series II: Archive Material
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society Lbrary
A catalogue from an exhibition of Stummer's photographs of Newark, New Jersey, No Easy Walk: Voices of the Inner City (Miami, FL: Frances Wolfson Art Gallery, Miami-Dade Community College, 1991), is held by the New-York Historical Society's Library.
Slides (photographs); Contact sheets.; Audiocassettes.; Gelatin silver prints.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Street life -- New York (State) -- New York.; Documentary photography -- New York (State) -- New York.; Poor -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Stummer, Helen M., 1936-
- Series I. Photographs, 1977-1980
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Photographs includes twenty-two 11x14 black and white photographs taken on East 6th Street between 1977 and 1980. The photographs have been loosely arranged by subject. Seven photographs show a woman named Shirley and her four children over a period of two years. Other photographs show individual portraits of children, street scenes of children and adults playing and lounging, and a few images of adults and children. Each photograph has been titled, dated, and signed by the photographer on the verso of each photograph. Titles recorded below are transcribed from the verso.
  Photographs are arranged loosely by subject, and thereunder by date. Titles are the photographer's.
  - Shirley and Family
    - Shirley and Cornell grooming their children, East 6th St. NYC, 1978 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Shirley, her four children - Sam, Charlie, Yvette, and Bernadette - in backyard with neighborhood - East 6th St. NYC, 1978 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Before Christening - Shirley in middle, Cornell on right with their children, 1978 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bernadette, Yvette, Charlie, and baby (Shirley's children), 1979 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Twins combing Shirley's hair - East 6th St. NYC, 1979 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shirley with baby in gutter water - East 6th St. NYC, 1979 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shirley's twin daughter Yvette in kitchen, 1979 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Children and Adults
    - Lenny holding Michelle, 1977 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nancy (pregnant belly). Her daughter Michelle imitating, East 6th St. NYC, 1978 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pedro holding his niece (bike in foreground) East 6th St. NYC, 1978 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Helen and Charlie, 1980 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Children
    - The Graduate, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2 girls with dolls, 1977 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Boy with glasses in lower east side lot, 1977 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alberto E 6th St. NYC, 1978 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Groups of Children
    - Neighborhood friends East 6th St. NYC, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Volleyball in front of Sloan Center street - East 6th St. NYC, 1978 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Playing in street - hydrant water - East 6th St. NYC, 1979 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Summer camp marching orders- East 6th St. NYC, 1979 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Other Groups
    - Woman, garbage, and dog, 1977 September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Her foot was amputated after getting ganguerene [sic] from rat bite. Woman's grandson by window overlooking East 6th St., 1979 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Hanging out"- local residents East 6th St. NYC, 1978 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II. Archive Material, 1977-2001
  Series II. Archive material includes material from Stummer's archive of the East 6th Street photography project. This includes contact sheets, slides, audiotapes, a 9 minute U-Matic cartridge "Children of East 6th Street" (which seems to be of still images), and a handmade artist's book of photographs and reminiscences of the project. This material spans the period from 1976 to 1984. The series also includes a manuscript memoir by Stummer titled "Risking Life and Lens: How I Photographed the Meanest Street in America and Why."
  One hundred and sixty printed contact sheets document the entirety of the images taken by Stummer on East 6th Street. Stummer's notes, as well as dates, are recorded on most of these. One hundred and sixty one slides, both black and white and Ektachrome, represent a selection of the images. Few are dated or labeled. The ten audiotapes include several that Stummer recorded of ambient noise on the block while she was taking photographs. It also includes a tape of her narration to a slide show of photos of East 6th Street. Several tapes are oral histories and interviews between Stummer and East 6th Street residents. One tape is an oral history interview with Irwin Silver concerning the September 11, 2001, attack on the World Trade Center.
  - Contact Sheets, 1977-1984 (Offsite-box 2, Folder unknown container)
  - "East Sixth Street," artist's book, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memoir "Risking Life and Lens: How I Photographed the Meanest Street in America and Why", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Slides, 1976-1980 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - U-Matic Cartridge "Children of East 6th Street, NYC", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Audiotapes, 1978-2001 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)